This is fantastic.
(Muroya) Right?
（Yoshida） This is why I can't stop going to Otaru.
（Muroya）Wow!
（Yoshida）Oh...
Ah, I knew it...
（Muroya）Bite into it and the meat juices of happiness
coming gushing out!
（Yoshida）It's beautifully presented.
（Mr Tayama）Hahahaha
（Narrator）Facing Ishikari Bay
Otari, a town that has flourished as a port town since ancient times.
Lots of historical buildings.
Hokkaido's leading town of tourism.
Today we are touring the shops that Otaru locals frequent.
And our guide is...
Hello I am Kanako Muroya (HBC Announcer).
Today we're going to explore the town of Otaru at a leisurely pace.
Well then, I'll be touring with this gentleman.
（Yoshida, reciting a haiku）
Standing and drinking, abandoning love on the canals of winter.
I am Rui Yoshida, hello, nice to meet you.
Nice to meet you.
（吉田）I, sort of strangely decided to, you know, in front of this canal...
Ah and in one hand you have...
Yes if I don't have this then the day doesn't start.
Rui Yoshida
（ナレーター）Lover of alcohol and mountain climbing
(Bottom text) Author of numerous books on drinking and travel, and a national figure as a representative of ‘bar culture’.
Continuing his travels all over Japan
Even so, Rui is especially drawn to the charms of Hokkaido.
（Yoshida）hmm?
（Reciting a haiku）
（Narrator）His other face is that of the industry's foremost pub poet, who organises haiku enthusiasts' groups.
So what encounters await us in the Hokkaido port town of Otaru?
A tour of local delicacies frequented by Otaru locals.
Port Town Walks in Hokkaido with Rui Yoshida
（Yoshida）Its not exactly
the backstreets of Otaru but...
（Muroya）Yeah this area is...
Wait a minute, there's a noren curtain swaying over there...
There's a food stall.
（Muroya）Shall we go and have a look?
I'm quite curious.
（Yoshida）Ah its candy
（Muroya）Candy?
Ah it says "candy" in the sign.
A candy stall…
（Yoshida）That's the first time I've seen something like that.
How nostalgic!
（Narrator）Rui was drawn in by the swaying noren curtains
but it's not a pub but rather a candy stall.
（Muroya）Ah there is a shop inside...
Ah hello!
（Mrs Ametani）I am a candy seller.
（Muroya）Candy seller？
（Mrs Ametani）Please go ahead, ye
It is the candy we make ourselves.
（Yoshida）So this is a manufacturing company?
(Mrs Ametani) That is correct, this is a factory.
We are the seventh generation.
（Muroya）Wow seventh generation!
(TN) Ameya or Ametani, literally candy valley, but here pronounced like "candy seller"
It says “飴谷”...
Your surname is Ameya?
Yes our last name is Ametani
（Muroya）Mrs Ametani？
（Mrs Ametani）Yes
（Yoshida）Ametani!
That's a rare name!
（Muroya）Right.
（Yoshida）It's almost as if you were born to be a candy seller.
（Mrs Ametani）Indeed.
（Muroya）Rui are you having any?
（Mrs Ametani）These are our cute and pretty apple candies
（Muroya）Rui, I am from Aomori.
（Yoshida）Really?!
（Muroya）Yeah Aomori!
Ah this sweetness...
Its super nostalgic.
（Muroya）mmm
（Yoshida）Ah but Aomori the home of apples
Its a gentle sweetness
Delicous (said in Aomori/Tsugaru dialect)
（Yoshida）How do you say candy in Tsugaru dialect?
Amekko (lit. little candy)
(Yoshida) Amekko
(Saying the candy is delicious in Aomori dialect)
The flagship store of the candy seller Rokubei
（Narrator）Founded in year 7 of the Taishou era (1918).
But the company's history goes all the way back to the Edo period.
These days you rarely see it, that is, authentic handmade candy.
Hokkaido beet sugar and Otaru water.
Made with simple ingredients there are around 50 kinds of candy.
Both the ingredients and production method haven't changed since back in the day.
（Yoshida･Muroya）Hello!
（Mrs Ametani）I am a candy seller.
（Woman）It's a nostalgic feeling, sweet but not too sweet.
But it tastes kind of comforting.
（Narrator）
The candy with the conforting flavour is the Yukitan (snow coal) candy.
Snow piling on top of coal in candy form, it is the taste of Hokkaido in winter.
（Muroya） So, Rui, there's a shop around here that's got the perfect snacks for drinks.
This is this place that is already famous in Otaru, Kamaei, selling Kamaboko fish cakes.
（Yoshida）Yes I can see it from the sign already, Kamaei.
（Muroya）It's a shop with history...
（Narrator）
Otaru City Hanazono district, gives off a downtown atmosphere.
In the corner, Kamaei, a shop selling kamaboko.
A famous shop even among famous shops,
secret gourmet menus are found on the menu!
（Muroya）This is the bread roll you're famous for, isn't it?
（Shop assistant）Inside the surimi, there's minced meat, onions and pepper,
（Shop assistant）It's rolled up in a thin slice of bread and deep-fried.
Mmm!
I'm sorry I suddently feel like drinking wine.
Aah wine is it?
（Narrator）Kamaei kamaboko fish cakes made from fish from nearby waters.
The same deliciousness unchanged since the founding in 1905.
The bread roll that even surprises Rui.
In 1962, the company head wanted to eat kamaboko in snack form...
... and from that idea this food item came into being.
As local delivery is not possible, many fans come to the shop in search of the freshly fried food.
(Woman) Bread roll.
（Yoshida）Oh, I knew it. The bread roll.
So you are going with the bread roll?
（Woman）Ah yes the bread roll.
（Narrator）
Apart from the bread roll
the mayo sandwich where mayonnaise and hot peppers are
the key ingredients is also popular.
These fried fish cakes are a regular side dish for the locals.
Miso nanban?
（Yoshida）Huh?
“Pungently spicy, scallions” also “with chili”
This, also, would go well with a drink.
（Yoshida）Aah I want to go for it.
It's obvious that you feel like drinking after these snacks.
（Yoshida） I'd like to taste a bit of the miso flavour.
Ah slightly sweet...
I want to pair this with dry sake.
This, the taste of the miso paste, the aroma spreads in the mouth so much.
Yes, the taste of the miso too, but...
also the spiciness of the chili...
（吉田）Uhm...sorry can you also do my "Wandering Pub Diary" show for me as well?
(Narrator) After Otaru's famous fish cakes, is it time to get some of you know what Rui?
（Yoshida）This place is pretty spacious, isn't it?
What?
There's some kind of food stall village over there.
（Yoshida）Now this is...
（Muroya）How nice!
（Yoshida）This...we have to drink now, don't we?
（Muroya）
Ah Rui, I was wondering when you would say that.
We found it.
（Yoshida）This is "Brick Valley" isn't it.
（Muroya）Let's go and have a look.
（Yoshida）There are a lot here...
（Narrator）
The sun is starting to set...
Now to the real food stalls.
（Mr Arasawa）
Buona sera!
‘Buona sera’, this vibe, is suddenly a great vibe, isn't it?
(Narrator) Italian food stall.
〝Kafe Dainingu RengaW〞
First up, a sparkling toast.
（Mr Arasawa）Here you go
（Yoshida）Oooh...
Now this is… Let's cheers.
（Mr Arasawa）Yes, by all means.
Cheers!
（Muroya）Cheers.
Alright, alright cheers.
Ahh hello, hello, hello
Sorry for butting in.
（Muroya）Hello
（Narrator）At the bar, greeting local regulars.
This is Rui Yoshida's toast.
Delicious, isn't it?
It's nice, isn't it? It's so refreshing.
（Mr Arasawa) This is a white whelk from Yoichi.
Steamed in white wine, whirling them out and eat them.
（Yoshida） Still some firmness left… and washing down with refreshing sparkling…
it's the best isn't it?
(Narrator) The snacks start at 200 yen per plate.
Pleasantly priced Italian food.
The owner mixes Otaru ingredients with his own taste from his travels in Italy.
Here are intense flavours.
（Muroya） What is this black stuff?
（Mr Arasawa）This is garlic from Akaigawa but,
We keep them in a rice cooker on the "keep warm" setting.
..for 20 hours
（Muroya）What?!
And then they become like this
（Yoshida）Ah this is dried up.
（Muroya）Ah but the inside is a bit soft.
You need a bit of courage to eat it.
（Yoshida）Ah this is sweet isn't it?
（Mr Arasawa）Yes it's sweet
It smells a bit of pistacchio
（Yoshida）Yeah!
It's the first time I try this.
（Mr Arasawa）Ah is that so?
（Narrator）Black garlic from Akaigawa
Slowly matured in a rice cooker for 20 hours.
A dish that brings out the umami.
（Yoshida）You're a bit of a connoisseur, aren't you?
The more I go to Italy, the more I like this kind of thing.
This sort of style.
That thing over there is a bit different from the counter, isn't it?
（Muroya）They are waving at us.
Good evening, what's that over there?
That counter, what are you selling?
（Mr Sanada）This is sort of a sushi place.
（Muroya）A sushi place!
（Narrator）A sushi counter inside an Italian restaurant?
The keyword you can't miss when talking about Otaru is ‘sushi’.
Umm... I'm curious!
（Narrator）
‘Good people, good taste.
good drunkenness.
Rui Yoshida, a pub poet who travels all over Japan.
Port Town Tour of Otaru
Rengayokocho (Brick Alley) Italian restaurant with an unexpected discovery.
（Muroya）Good evening, what's that over there?
That counter, what are you selling?
（Mr Sanada）This is sort of a sushi place.
（Muroya）A sushi place!
(Narrator) Wow what a surprise - beyond the counter of the Italian bar - is a sushi restaurant!
（Yoshida）You can also eat there?
That's right, but the business is completely separate.
May I take something from there?
（Mr Arasawa）By all means.
I would like some sushi!
（Mr Sanada）Sushi yes!
Ehm is 6 pieces alright?
（Yoshida）6 pieces please
（Mr Sanada）Understood
(TN) Untranslatable joke, "sixth sense" and "the sixth piece (of sushi)" is pronounced the same in Japanese
Somehow, with my sixth sense...
（Men in the back, laughing）“Sixth sense”
There it is, the old man joke.
(Narrator) Ruis engine is already running at full throttle!
Authentic artisanal standing sushi.
Sushi restaurant ‘ 高大 (Kodai)’.
While the sushi is being made, Rui adds some white wine.
Still, I was surprised to find such a fun place to eat, you know.
(Muroya) We're very close to the other customers.
（Mr Arasawa）That's right.
They gradually mingle like this.
（Muroya）Ah! Rui, the sushi...
（Mr Sanada）Sushi
（Yoshida）This is amazing
（Muroya）Otaru is famous for sushi, isn't it?
I think I'll get on the bandwagon and have a glass of white wine.
White wine, yes! White, please.
（Mr Arasawa）Understood!
（Yoshida）Hehe, this is an interesting combination.
(Narrator) The sushi that makes you want to add a glass of white wine.
Delicious nigiri with a focus on fish from the waters around Otaru is lined up.
This is six pieces for 1,000 yen.
（Muroya） I think I'll have the salmon roe, then.
Mmm!
Delicious with a pop.
Rui-san, I've never had sake and wine together before.
No, no, no, it's, um, sushi and wine isn't it?
Ahh haha...
What did I just say?
（Yoshida）Sake and wine.
（Muroya）Excuse me.
I'm getting a bit drunk.
I'm having fun.
（Yoshida）With this kind of vibe... I can't turn back now.
（Mr Sanada）You can't turn back now?
Can I order a few more?
Yes
(Applause)
(Sanada) Thank you very much.
（Woman）Rui!
（Man）Rui!
Just... just for a minute, let's go toast over there.
(Muroya) Yeah, right.
（Yoshida）Oh, here... here, it's a different atmosphere.
（Mr Sanada）Welcome!
（Yoshida）This is nice isn't it?
Cheers!
Oh, thank you, thank you, thank you...
It's great, isn't it?
What are you drinking?
（Man）Potato spirits on the rock …
(Mr Sanada) Potato on the rocks there it is!
（Muroya）Potato on the rocks, very nice!
It's alright its only the sixth cup
（Mr Sanada）“Only” hahaha...
（Yoshida）Nice mood.
（Muroya）Right? Fun.
（Mr Arasawa）It's... but, you know, when you do it every night, you can't stop.
It's... it's fun.
(Muroya) Chef!
What is your recommendation?
It's already ready.
（Muroya）Thank you!
No, no, no.
Wait, wait, wait, wait.
Abashiri caught broadbanded thornyhead (kinki).
And fresh herring from Abashiri.
and then spear squid
This is art isn't it
（Mr Sanada）Art? Ahaha...
Beautiful!
(Mr Sanada) You may say so...
（Narrator）Truly sushi art!
The head chefs seasonal 3 nigiri recommendations.
Stunning workmanship.
You know, when it comes to this...
It's OK without any comments, you know?
（Muroya）Abashiri herring
Umm delicious!
Chef! Dewishush!
（Mr Sanada）“Dewishush”
（Muroya）Delicious (in Aomori dialect)!
（Yoshida）
“Delicious”  (in Aomori dialect)
that means "This is a rare delicacy."
This is Aomori dialect.
（Muroya）It's incredibly fatty and delicious.
This is... Otaru... you know...
（Mr Arasawa）Spear squid
（Yoshida）Yes
This is also delicious (Aomori dialect)
（Muroya）Delicious！ (Aomori dialect)
(Narrator) The last dish is Otaru's spear squid.
Taste of the Sea of Japan with its natural sweetness.
Here, against the pub poet Rui.
Kanako Muroya suddenly has a haiku.
Gentle breeze
Pororin Kararin
Otaru candy/rain (same pronounciation)
（Customers）ｈｍｍｍ...
No no, this is... quite pleasing to the ear.
（Yoshida）Um...
We went to eat Otaru candy.
（Muroya）We did.
（Yoshida）There's a food stall.
（Mr Arasawa）It was raining in the morning.
（Muroya）Yes, that's right!
（Yoshida）Ah, you understood very well.
It's a play on the words ‘candy’ and ‘rain’...
You know what I mean!
I love it.
（Laughter）
This is a problem, isn't it?
（Muroya）It's getting fun...
(Narrator) When the lanterns are lit.
The town of Otaru is tinged with laughter.
(Customers) Cheers!
(Narrator) Next is a Western-style pub where Otaru locals gather.
Kanako Muroya is smitten with bacon on a scale she's never seen before!
(Something in Aomori dialect)
I'll translate it for you now...
（Yoshida）Well, that was some fun, that standing bar.
It was!
（Yoshida）I mean...
I feel like I want to spread that sort of thing across the country already.
It's still early.
（Muroya）Yes.
Here!
（Yoshida）Here also, still...
Look at this place, too, how different it looks.
It's “Ponkasu” right?
（Muroya）It's not “Ponkasu”
It's “Sukanpo”
（Yoshida）Ah “Sukanpo”
It's reverse
（Yoshida）Ah I see.
（Narrator）〝Relaxation pub Sukanpo〞
Western-style pub where Otaru locals gather.
（Yoshida）Excuse me for a moment, do you mind if I jump in next to you?
（Man）Not at all.
（Yoshida）Sorry.
（Muroya）Excuse me.
（Mr Tayama）Thrice poured...
（Yoshida）Huh？ This, thrice poured, what is that?
（Muroya）Thrice poured?
（Mr Tayama）It will take a bit of time
（Muroya）How long?
(Mr Tayama)
It will take 5 min.
(Narrator) Three times poured beer that takes five minutes to complete.
Even a pub connoisseurs like Rui has never heard of this menu.
What on earth is it?
He just drew it a bit like this and then left it...
Is that the first pour?
Yes that's the first pour...
(Narrator) First there's the first pour.
It's going to take a while, so Rui's party ordered some other beers.
Here, too, it's also...
（Yoshida）May I?
Excuse me. Thank you very much.
（Customers）Cheers！
（Yoshida）Hello
（Muroya）Just now, it's the second pour.
It takes time...
（Yoshida）This will probably take until tomorrow.
(Narrator) It's five minutes, five minutes.
(Yoshida) There are things like bacon steaks
（Mr Tayama）It's from a place called Akaigawa Village, and they use Kurobuta pork...
It's aged bacon, but ...
Can I go to the bathroom first?
Haha... bathroom? Please, by all means...
I don't think it's done yet.
It's not good for you to hold it in, you know, so please, go ahead...
Has the third pour happened yet?
（Mr Tayama）It's done!
（Muroya）Is it done? Oh, I see!
Then let's just say it's not done yet.
No, it's a drink that doesn't work like that.
（Muroya）Rui's gone to the bathroom. What should I do...
This! This is the rumoured three-times-poured beer.
I think I'll have a drink. Sorry about that, Rui.
Aah! It different isn't it?
（Mr Tayama）Yes
Um... mellow...
（Mr Tayama）Yes, that is right.
Delicious bubbles that go right into your mouth!
Rui quickly! Isn't he done yet?
The bubbles are disappearing...
（Narrator）
First pour… second pour…
Third pour
The beer that takes time to finish is...
Moderately decarbonated.
enhancing the taste of the beer.
A gem of a drink, even if you have to wait a long time for it.
Oh, Rui, I'm sorry I drank before you.
This is the three times poured?
（Muroya）This is it
Once again...
（Yoshida）Well then...
（Yoshida･Muroya）Cheers!
Wow, it's super creamy!
Isn't this like a beer that's meant to be drunk for this foam? This ...
（Muroya）Ah… wow!！
（Yoshida）Oh...
Ah, I knew it...
Right? It's beautiful.
（Mr Tayama）Thank you very much.
Well, it's bacon and eggs.
We use natural eggs from Yoichi.
（Muroya）Wait, this yolk!
The yolk is very...
（Yoshida）It's full of sun.
It's full of sun.…
Given the name “Full of sun.”
（Muroya）
I've never had such thick bacon before!
It's very delicious (Aomori dialect)
It's super duper delicious (even more Aomori dialect)
I'll translate it for you now...
‘You... you don't get to eat this very often’.
‘Such a delicious taste’...
Goo!
（Mr Tayama）Thank you very much!
（Yoshida）Is it okay without translating that?
That was standard Japanese just now.
(Narrator) Handmade taste, painstakingly produced on the farm.
Aged bacon steaks from Kurobuta pork
（Mr Tayama）The yolk's colour changes with the seasons.
鶏たちが食べる餌が変わるので
（Yoshida･Muroya）Really?!
（Mr Tayama）Right now they eat a lot of pumpkins, leftover pumpkin...
（Yoshida）And that's why there's this yellow colour...
If it's like this then...
I gradually feel like order more from the menu.
Thank you very much
（Muroya）What are you eating?
（Man）It's kakuni (stew of cubed ingredients)
（Muroya）Wow, looks tasty!
（Man）Tanaka kakuni
（Muroya）What was that?
（Man）Haha, I'm sorry...
（吉田）Well then, can you just confirm one more time
（TN）Pun, kakuni stew and confirm is pronounced similarly
（Man）Aah...
Oh, boy.
（Muroya）Oh, my God, they're all drunk.
(Narrator) Kakuni, a classic Japanese dish of stewed pork!
And speaking of ‘sukampo’ specialities, here is one!
Soba-rice with lots of sauce
How does it taste?
（Yoshida）This soba-rice
（Mr Tayama）Originally a food from the Kobe area.
I was over there for a while.
It was delicious at the time, so...
I'd really like to adopt it in my own shop.
Yakisoba, rice and...
（Yoshida）Mm!
Mmm!
(Muroya) Mmm!
（Yoshida）It's beautifully presented.
（Mr Tayama）Hahaha...
This is so refined.
（Muroya）Very refined!
（Customers）Cheers!
（Muroya）So you are not from Otaru?
（Mr Tayama）Correct
（Muroya）What brought you to Otaru?
On a journey.
（室谷）On a journey?
Yeah, I was just dropping by.
And I liked it very much.
I opened the shop to live in Otaru...
I think we're the same.
Um... please be my friend.
Master and Rui both love Hokkaido.
Right right.
I think so.
Ah, master.
Oh, thank you very so much for today.
No, no, thank you.
After this, at night in Otaru Rui Yoshida's haiku.
These bubbles...
These bubbles... for these bubbles...
New sake when the tongue is smacking, God's dance (haiku)
- Rui Yoshida
There's a friend on the other side of this drink...
（Muroya）Aa…
This makes you happy, doesn't it?
That's deep, isn't it? I didn't think of it that way at all.
I was just drinking...
No, from now on, you have to feel it.
You don't have to think about it.
You feel it.
（Yoshida）Feel it.
（Narrator）
Good drinks and good food.
We enjoyed the port town of Otaru.