（Muroya）It looks delicious!
The meat is so flaky
Woaah!
So this ikameshi... is...  ehm... very popular?
(pun on ika=squid, ika ni=very)
Was that a pun?
No no...
Did you just make a pun?
（Yoshida）Hahaha...
I am stuck in the whelk of laughter
(lit. translation, untranslatable pun)
(Narrator)
Dad's jokes are going strong, huh?
Port Town Walks in Hokkaido with Rui Yoshida
Today, we have a wide variety of the finest products from the beach.
The sea urchin is delicious, and the squid is also very crisp.
And the sake also delicious.
Eh! Hey, look at this.
That's amazing... Mother...
That's good education.
(Woman) The parent is drinking barley tea.
(Narrator) What port town did we visit today?
Hello!
My name is Kanako Muroya (HBC Announcer)
Here we are in Hakodate!
Hakodate Morning Market
Now, I'm looking forward to seeing what kind of delicious food we will be eating this time.
and of course, this is the gentleman who will be touring with me!
This gentleman... this gentleman...
Hehe... Rui
（Yoshida）Ah…
Are you already eating and drinking, Rui?
I am Rui Yoshida
It's early!
It's delicious!
It's a nice atmosphere, isn't it?
Today, we are going to...
many other places as well so
come on. We don't have any more time for this.
Let's go. Let's go.
Then let's go.
(Narrator) At the morning market in Hakodate
Today, as well, wandering around with a drink in one hand.
Rui Yoshida
(Bottom text) Author of numerous books on drinking and travel, and a national figure as a representative of ‘bar culture’.
（Narrator）Lover of alcohol and mountain climbing
Continuing his travels all over Japan
（Reciting a haiku）
（Narrator）His other face is that of the industry's foremost pub poet, who organises haiku enthusiasts' groups.
So what encounters could await us today?
Port Town Walks in Hokkaido with Rui Yoshida
Hakodate edition
A tram running through town
Hakodate Bay stretches out before your eyes
Surrounded by the sea, Hakodate, one of Hokkaido's three largest cities.
With a thriving fishing industry...
There are many specialties such as squid and ramen noodles.
Numerous historic buildings can be seen on the streets of this nostalgic port town.
Rui, this is Kaisen Ichiba seafood market, not far from Hakodate Station.
There are many things.
（Yoshida）I see...
It looks totally fresh.
（Shop assistant） Like this one, which is in season right now...
（Yoshida） Oh, this is also splendid, isn't it, summer salmon?
The blue of the sea is still there.
It's the color of the ocean, isn't it? -This one.
（Muroya） What a beautiful color.
（Shop assistant）The fresh one is bluish like this.
(Yoshida) Do you know what this is?
(Muroya) What is the first character?
(Shop assistant) It's "ku".
（Yoshida） Kue? (longtooth grouper)
（Muroya） Kue?
（Shop assistant） Wrong.
(Muroya) Eh... It's not?
（Shop assistant）It's "Kurozoi" (black rock fish)
（Muroya) Rui, do you know much about fish?
（Yoshida）Not at all, I don't know many of the names
I known about eating them
(Narrator) Two people who specialize in eating.
Lured by delicious aromas, they move to the back of the market.
There you will find a luxurious gem that offers a taste of Hakodate's specialties!
Which shall we start with?
（Yoshida） Um...it's probably hot, right? (grilled scallops)
You can try first
Can't you eat hot foods？ Rui
（Yoshida）No no...
(Muroya) How lovely, isn't it?
Mmm!
Delicous! The meat is so tender.
（Yoshida）Ah...
（Murotani）The aroma of the seashore is so good... Delicious.
What happened?
An incident, an incident...
(Narrator) Huh? What happened?
The hot broth on Rui's hand...
But for the sake of a pub poet's pride...
regardless of incidents, the show must go on
The more you taste it the more the sweetness comes out
(Narrator)
As expected of Rui.
The follow-up musings were also boldly reported... or what?
Suddenly the god of puns descended upon us.
Is this ikameshi? (squid filled with rice)
（Shop assistant）Yes this is ikameshi
After all Hakodate is famous for ikameshi.
So this ikameshi... is...  ehm... very popular?
(pun on ika=squid, ika ni=very)
Was that a pun?
No no...
Did you just make a pun?
（Yoshida）Hahaha...
No I didn't
（Muroya）That's such a dad joke
Rui when you eat whelks you can't stop laughing
Is there some laughing potion in there?
(Yoshida) No...
I am stuck in the whelk of laughter
(lit. translation, untranslatable pun)
(Narrator) Let's finish the punny whelks there...
Walking further into the market...
（Yoshida） Uh...
(Muroya) Ah it's steaming... Rui... Hakodate's Tanabe company's
squid shumai (steamed meat dumplings)
Very famous
(Yoshida) Is it really?
（Shop assistant）Packing all the goodness of Hokkaido into one package...
（Shop assistant）We use Hokkaido wheat for the dough
It's not at all how it looks.
Inside, there are mostly pieces of squid.
The sweetness spreads in the mouth...
This is calling out for a drink
（Shop assistant）Mr Rui here is some white wine
I've got it for you. Here you go.
White wine?
（Muroya）How nice
(Narrator) Look at that!
From the tasting corner, unexpected wine!
Rui, how do white wine and squid shumai go together?
Just as I thought...
（Shop assistant）Do they match?
perfectly
(Narrator) The Hakodate tour starts with seafood and white wine
Next, traditional Japanese sweets
The taste of a long-established restaurant for four generations located at the foot of Mount Hakodate.
（Yoshida）Hello
（Yoshida･Muroya）
Hello
（Shop assistant）
Welcome
(Muroya)
There are many kinds of mochi.
（Mr. Sato)
Rather than a Japanese confectionery, my shop is really a classic... traditional mochi shop.
(Narrator) Founded in year 33 of the Meiji Era.
(Narrator)
A mochi shop with over 100 years of history.
Four generations of unwavering commitment to handmade products.
(Mr. Sato) We cook everything ourselves...
from boiling azuki beans to make bean paste...
to the mugwort which I go to pick myself
you know I work all day inside so it's nice to go outside and get some sun once in a while
(Narrator) Daifuku made from mugwort that the owner himself picked in the mountains.
Let's try it now!
（Yoshida）
What a nostalgic sweetness!
and the aroma of mugwort spreads.
It's like when I was a kid...
You know? I was born in the mountains.
I recall those days.
(Muroya) Heh heh heh...
(Narrator) And one more item.
The other item is a signature product of the store.
A gold medal winner in a national confectionary competition...
bekomochi (leaf shaped mochi)
(Muroya)
It has a slight sweetness to it.
The texture is really nice.
The rice is properly pounded with a pestle, so the firmness of the rice is different.
That one you see over there...
(Yoshida) Is it that one?
It's like we built this restaurant with that thing.
Here my mom was working...
（Muroya）Ah your mother?
（Mr. Sato）
and I was always following her around
(Narrator) A mother who has been watching over the store for many years
and inheriting the taste Hideaki Sato, the fourth generation
and even these hands bear witness to that history
See here...
the left and right are clearly different
（Yoshida）Ah...
(Mr. Sato)
Yes, it's from all the squeezing and gripping of the mochi.
It's a blessing to be able to make it even when customers come over.
(Narrator)
Mochi passed down through the hands of artisans
The taste of over 100 years of tradition.
Well then Rui, next is another handmade store but...
in Hakodate…
well also in Hokkaido in general, this is rare...
a shop that handmakes this sort of thing
（Yoshida）Ah…
By the looks of it, you can tell it's guitars, right?
（Muroya）Yes this is a store that makes handmade guitars
(Yoshida)
All we can do is to go in and have a peek.
(Narrator)
A handmade guitar store
〝Aventure Guitars〞
You can always hear the sound of guitars coming from here.
（Yoshida）Ah yes yes
(Narrator)
The Kawagoe couple is always smiling.
From Tokyo, they returned back to their hometown, Hakodate, and started this shop.
What kind of…
（Mr. Kawagoe）Ah me? I love the Beatles
（Yoshida）
Aah the beatles
And the wife?
（Mrs. Kawagoe）I like Luna Sea
(Mr. Kawagoe) There is a bit of a generational gap there
（Muroya）Your wife is a bit young...
（Mr. Kawagoe）Indeed
(Narrator) It's been three whole years since they opened.
It has become a place where many electric and folk guitar lovers gather.
(Playing Sanya Blues by Nobuyasu Okabayashi)
Bring some shochu! (song mentions drinking shochu)
（Kawagoe）
Try and make some sound
now that you've came all the way to the store
（Yoshida）Yeah
Up means higher notes right?
（Mr. Kawagoe）No
Huh, no?
（Yoshida）It's the same as a shamisen
（Muroya）So...
（Yoshida）Well then shall we leave?
（Muroya）The sound is reverberating
（Yoshida）It's nice
(Narrator) After the guitar, it's an unexpected museum in Hakodate
A hero of the closing days of the Tokugawa Shogunate
Sakamoto Ryoma Memorial Hall
Dreaming of emigrating to Hokkaido, Sakamoto Ryoma's favorite things and
related items are on display.
This is a major checkpoint for Rui, who is also a tourism ambassador for Kochi Prefecture!
But it's about time for a drink.
（Yoshida）Wow this is…
（Mr. Fukaya）
The pride of Hakodate “King shiitake”
(Narrator) Giant Shiitake Mushrooms, a specialty of the southern Hokkaido region
What exactly is this so-called "King shiitake" mushroom?
(Narrator) Port Town Hakodate Tour with Rui Yoshida
Where is the next stop?
I will just go ahead and take a seat here...
( Muroya) It looks... a lot like my grandma's house.
(Yoshida) The glass in the front is from the Taisho era.
How do you know?
（Yoshida）The quiver...
(Muroya)
Eh... Taisho era?
(Yoshida)
Taisho era glass.
(Narrator)
The unique warping of the...
somehow nostalgic Taisho glass
It's like we've suddenly stepped back in time. This is...
a Spanish style bar
La Concha
First floor is Japanese style
Second floor is Western style
A store with an evocative and elegant atmosphere.
The house where the owner-chef was born.
a rice wholesale store converted into a Spanish-style bar
（Bartender）
Here you go
La Concha
(Narrator) Once thirst has been quenched, a quick meal is in order.
Pickled Hokkaido herring in vinegar
Overwintered May Queen patatas bravas
Self-produced Spanish style sausages with vivid colour
（Muroya）Amberjack carpaccio？
（Bartender）Yes
Ah... lightly seasoned
They are all very friendly flavours
Maybe it's the chef's personality that is coming out
(Narrator) Dishes that show the personality of the chef.
This one, cod and clams in a parsley sauce is also an unmissable recommendation
（Mr. Fukaya･Yoshida）
Ah hello
（Mr. Fukaya）Um, south Hokkaido, Hakodate's pride, "King Shiitake" mushroom
（Yoshida）
When I said that the personality is showing in the dishes...
I thought it might be someone with this kind of face.
exactly like this
（Mr. Fukaya）Ah is that so?
(Narrator)
The dish that is the pride of Mr. Fukaya who was just as imagined
King shiitake mushroom ajillo
Mr. Fukuda in Nanae Town produces shiitake mushrooms of the size you see!
Called "King shiitake" mushroom
It is a hidden specialty of Hakodate!
Now, how does it taste?
So much of the fresh flavour remains
(Muroya) Delicious!
（Yoshida）Right?
(Mr. Fukaya) Old people can't eat steak anymore. Their teeth are too weak.
I made this to be a replacement for that.
（Muroya）The cured ham also...
（Yoshida）Yeah…
(Mr. Fukaya) This we've been making ourselves for 28 years.
It's a little less salty than the Spanish...
you can feel the sweetness
（Yoshida）I can feel it
(Narrator) 28 years of making cured ham
A carefully crafted product with a hint of sweetness.
Aged slowly for 1 year and 4 months
The umami flavor is brought out to the maximum extent possible!
(Muroya) Mr. Fukaya, did you live in Spain?
I, um... about 37 years ago...
I was in a town in the Basque Country called San Sebastian.
I've been training there for three years.
Right over there.
（Yoshida）I thought this was the night view of Hakodate.
(Muroya)
But it looks very similar to Hakodate.
But returning to your hometown, and serving up more and more of this incredible and authentic food....
A society that forms relations over drinks
Well, in other words, Hakodate's ability to integrate with
the Spanish drinking culture is one of the
most profound things about Hakodate, after all.
Ah~... this.
What are you drinking?
(Woman) Sangria.
(Yoshida) Ah...
It's delicious, too.
I love the Basque Country in Spain.
（Woman）Every year I go two times
(Muroya)
Eh~! Is that so?
(Yoshida) Cheers...
Oh... a married couple?
(Woman) Yes, we are.
(Muroya)
Did you meet in Japan?
Yes, yes, here.
Here in Hakodate
(Man) In Hakodate
(Narrator) Cross-border socializing
And encounters, and good drinks...
make Hakodate nights fun!
(Muroya) What is it about Hakodate that attracts you to the city?
I think this place has
that kind of atmosphere
that is closer to Europe than Tokyo.
For example, in front of this Kanamori warehouse cluster.
If you go up this hill, there's a church here.
(Yoshida) The history is amazing, isn't it?
( Mr. Fukaya )
A little Western excitement.
...with an air of romance.
I think that's nice, you know.
（Mr. Ookubo）♪ The sea urchin (singing)～！
♪ The sea urchin (singing)～！
(Narrator) In a hidden gem of a tavern, where songs and laughter abound...
Rui was very moved
(Yoshida) Ah...
( Both of them ) Delicious~!
(Izakaya Yamabuki
Shinonomecho, Hakodate)
(Muroya) This restaurant
(Yoshida) Charcoal Grill
Yes "Izakaya"
(Yoshida) Oooh...
(Muroya) Ah...
It's bustling with people.
(Yoshida, Muroya)
Good evening.
（Muroya)
Mister, how many years have you been here?
(Mr. Ookubo)
Ummm... in May.
It will be 34 whole years.
（Murotani.)
Wow...
It's freezing cold.
（Muroya) Oh, it's ice cold.
（Yoshida)
Hello, hello, hello
（Woman）
Oh, I'm so happy!
(Yoshida) Hello hello
（Muroya) Rui.
This is the menu.
(The whole menu is written in Japanese kanji puns)
（Yoshida) Is this the kanji for “man”?
What is this?
（Muroya）(Trying to decipher
the puns) hi... ka... rei...
karei (flounder)! How fun!
San...
（Yoshida）This is sanma
(mackerel pike, written using kanji for birth and horse)
Ah iwashi (pilchard, written stomach eagle
Hokke (Okhotsk Atka mackerel​, written Treasure - K)
（Yoshida, Murotani)
Kinki (broadfin thornyhead, written Gold - 2)
It's a bother, isn't it?
(Narrator)
This is a bit of an unusual menu list but...
They ordered the most highly recommended dish, grilled whole mackerel pike.
(Muroya)
Do you come to this restaurant often?
(Woman)
This is my mom. She's been coming here for 25 years.
(Muroya) Oh, my!
(Yoshida)
So you've been going there since you were 20 years old?
(Woman) Ahahahaha!
Thank you very much.
I'm so flattered. Hahahahaha...
(Narrator) The afore mentioned mackerel pike has been grilled.
（Muroya）Wow!
(Yoshida)
Can this be grilled in this shape?
（Muroya）Ah it looks delicious!
The meat is so flaky!
Woaah!
(Mr. Ookubo)
If you like, you can make it into a bracelet and take it home.
You betcha, you betcha.
It looks so delicious!
(Narrator) A truly delicious looking whole roasted mackerel pike
It's satisfying to watch the bones slide right out.
(Yoshida) Ah...
（Both of them）Delicious~!
Here you go.
(Muroya) Oh... wow!
（Mr. Ookubo）♪ The sea urchin (singing)～！
♪ The sea urchin (singing)～！
Okay, that's all.
(Mr. Ookubo)
Today my voice is better than usual.
It was so much better than I expected.
(Muroya)
With this much included...
How expensive...
It's 2500 yen.
Is the price of the song included?
Not included.
(Narrator)
2,000 to 2,500 yen for a box of sea urchins
Mmm... how delightful.
This is grilled miso clams
(Muroya) Ah!
I love these!
(Mr. Ookubo)
Oh, really?
(Yoshida)
And what kind of song does this include...
(singing do-re-mi off-key)
...or something like that?
(Muroya) I don't need that one.
(Mr. Ookubo)
Okay... hahahahaha!
(Narrator)
Popular in Kanako Muroya's hometown Tsugaru region
Grilled beach specialties
Finally, a beaten egg is a nice touch.
This is delicious (in Tsugaru dialect)
（Yoshida.)
"This is something rare...?"
“I'll eat it after all.”
(Muroya) I said “It looks delicious.”
Is it good (again in Tsugaru dialect)?
（Yoshida）It's good
Isn't it great fun?
(Muroya)
Singing...
Singing songs I didn't ask order...
(Yoshida) It's good.
（Muroya) It's good. It's soothing.
Here's the thing.
I got fired from my last company.
(Muroya) Hahahaha!
(Mr. Ookubo)
This is a Hokkaido “Kunimare” dry sake.
（Yoshida)
This is bold, isn't it?
（Muroya）Tasty?
Delicious.
(Muroya) Ahhh...
That's nice.
(Yoshida) This is...
It's a shame to spill it.
I just can't help it. I have to go over here...
(Man)
Thank you very much.
（Muroya）Good evening
Oh, thank you. Thank you.
Thank you very much.
(Woman)
My younger sister and daughter...
Do you want some of this?
She's 22 years old.
So she likes to drink.
（Yoshida) Oh, you're 22?
Eh! Hey, look at this.
That's amazing... Mother...
That's good education.
The parent is drinking barley tea.
"Yamabuki" 's recommendations of today is...
Is the Hakodate stable over them all, squid sashimi
Rui, how is the taste?
This crispy feeling.
I really have never eaten squid this crunchy before!
(Muroya)
and the Mrs...
What kind of a person is your husband?
（Chiyoko）
A person that is fun to be around I think
(Muroya)
Oh, that's nice...
How nice!
(Muroya)
How nice
(Ookubo-san)
It was a workplace marriage. The Maritime Self-Defense Force.
(Muroya) What? Self-Defense Forces?
(Ookubo-san)
Yes, from 18.
(Yoshida)
Both of you were in the Maritime Self-Defense Force? Wow...
so I've been in the nightlife business for a long time
(slang for nightlife business is "water trade")
(Yoshida).
So to speak, “at sea”...
It's here.
（Yoshida.)
Here it comes!
(Kanako's haiku)
breezes of early summer
The seagull's troubles...
I wonder what they are.
I don't think seagulls have any troubles.
(Muroya) Haha!
If you give me an answer there, it's done...
I don't even know if there is one.
No, they don't.
They live by instinct.
(Worrying seagull pun)
(Narrator)
Now then, Rui, if you please.
A Summer Night's
(Rui's haiku)
Illumination
A Summer Night's
Bay Area
One more time please
（Yoshida）Sorry
Uhm...
If I have to tell it twice...
I guess that means it's still a bad piece of work on top of being drunk.
No, no, no...
Um... I don't mean to impress anyone.
Not today.
I'd rather enjoy myself.
(Mr. Ookubo)
Sake is also delicious... (singing)
(Narrator)
Good food, sake, songs and haiku
No, “fun” is the most important thing!
Hakodate Port Town Walk in Hokkaido with Rui Yoshida
Well, which port town shall we go to next?