This is marvelous isnt it?
Right?
Otaru, that's why I can't stop coming here.
Wauw
Ah, I knew it...
When you bite into it, you'll feel the meat juices of happiness.
bursting out
It's a beautifully finished product.
Hehehe
Facing Ishikari Bay
Otaru, a prosperous port town since ancient times
There are also many historical buildings
Hokkaido's leading sightseeing town
Today we're going to visit the establishments where Otaru locals go.
The guide is...
Hello, I am Muroya Kanako.
Today, we are going to explore the town of Otaru at a leisurely pace.
I will be exploring with this person right here
(Haiku) Standing and drinking, abandoning love in the canals of winter
My name is Yoshida Rui, hello
Hello
I just came to me at this canal
And in one hand of course...
Without this the day cannot begin
Yoshida Rui
Loves drinking and mountaineering
Continuing his travels all across Japan
In particular, Rui is a man who is fascinated by the charms of Hokkaido.
(reading a haiku)
His other face is that of a pub poet
who organizes a haiku lovers' association.
The top pub poet in the industry
Well then, in the port town of Otaru, Hokkaido
What kind of encounters await?
Let's go on a tour of local delicacies among Otaru's local gourmet food
When it comes to Otaru...
It's not exactly a back street but...
Yeah this area is very...
Wait a minute, are those shop curtains (noren) fluttering in the wind over there?
thats a food stall isnt it?
Shall we go check it out for a moment?
I'm very curious to see...
Ah, its candy
Candy?
Right "candy" is written on it
A candy sellers stall.
Its the first time I see such a thing.
How nostalgic
Rui was drawn in by the noren curtains of a food stall, however
instead of a pub he found a candy store
（室谷）あっ 中がお店になって…
Ah hello
I am a candy seller
Candy seller？
Yes
Its candy that we produce ourselves right here.
So this is a production company?
Indeed, this is a factory
I am the seventh generation
Wow, seventh generation?
And your name is "Ameya" (same pronunciation as "candy seller" in Japanese)?
Yes our family name is Ametani (lit. "candy valley" other pronunciation of the aforementioned kanji)
Mrs Ametani?
Yes
Ametani! Thats a rare name isnt it?
Right
Its almost like you were born to be a candy seller
It is isnt it?
Rui are you trying some?
These are some lovely, cute apple candies
Rui, you know, Im from Aomori (place famous for its apples)
It that right?
It is!
Ah, this sweetness
Very nostalgic
Uuhm
From the town of apples Aomori...
a gentle sweetness.
its delicious (said in Tsugaru dialect, i.e. Aomori)
How do you say "candy" in the Tsugaru dialect?
"Amekko"
The candy is delicious (said in Tsugaru dialect)
Candy shop Rokube, flagship store
Founded in the seventh year of the Taisho era
But the business traces its roots all the way back to the Edo period
Something that is rarely seen today, i.e. handmade candy
Hokkaidos beet sugar and Otarus water
Made using simple ingredient, there are around 50 varieties
Both the ingredients and the method has barely changed since back then
Hello
I am a candy seller!
Its very nostalgic, sweet, but not too sweet
but somehow a taste that makes you sigh
That candy that makes you sigh?
Snow coal candy
Recreating using candy, the look of snow piled on top of a lump of coal
The taste of winter in Hokkaido
So Rui, in this area there is shop that sells the perfect drinking snack
That is a place that is very famous in Otaru
Kamaei, a kamaboko (steamed fish paste) shop
Ah, I can already see the sign, Mr. Kamaei
A shop with history
A place that gives of a wiff of downtown atmosphere, Hanazono district, Otaru City
In one corner there is a store.
Kamaei kamaboko
A famous place even amongst famous places
a hidden gourmet menu discovery
Bread rolls are what this is famous for, right?
Inside the fish paste
there is minced meat, onion, and seasoned with black pepper
Then we wrap it in thin toast bread and deep fry it
mm
Sorry I suddently feel like drinking wine
Aah wine is it?
Made from fish from nearby seas
Kamaei's kamaboko fish cakes
The deliciousness that has not changed since the founding in 1905
The bread rolls that even surprised Rui
In 1962 the owner said "I wanted to create a way to eat kamaboko like a snack"
and the result is this
a product that can not be shipped
there are countless fans that want to have them freshly fried
Bread roll...
Ah, its the bread roll
Of course you are getting the bread roll right?
Yes the bread roll
Apart from the bread roll
mayonnaise and chili pepper being the key ingredients
the mayo-sandwich is popular
This fried fish cake
is a staple side dish for the locals.
What about the miso nanban (dish prepared using chili peppers and Welsh onions​)？
（吉田）えっ？
Spicy and hot with green onion and chili peppers
It looks like it would go well with sake.
Yes, I want to try it.
I feel like... this side dish
makes you want to drink alcohol...
This is something that is only natural isnt it?
I'd like to taste a bit of the miso flavor.
Oh, this is slightly sweet.
ah this would go well with dry sake
The taste and aroma of the miso spreads in your mouth.
and also the miso flavour
The spiciness of the
chili peppers is also...
Um, excuse me.
Could you do my "Bar Hopping Report" instead of me?
(Ruis old show where he visits pubs in Tokyo)
When it comes to Otarus pride, the kamaboko fish cakes
One suddently feels like "that" right Rui?
This place is pretty spacious, isn't it?
What?
There's some kind of street food fair over there.
Well this is...
How nice!
（吉田）この…
もう 飲むしかないんじゃないの？
（室谷）
あっ 類さん いつ その言葉を
言ってくださるかと思って
見つけちゃいましたね
（吉田）これ
“レンガ横丁”というね うわぁ…
（室谷）行きましょうよ ちょっと
（吉田）これ 結構
たくさんあるみたいですね ここ
（ナレーター）
日も傾き始め
今度こそ
本当の屋台へ
（荒澤さん）
ボナセーラ！
“ボナセーラ”という このノリ
いきなり すごいノリですね これは
（ナレーター）
イタリアン屋台の―
〝カフェ ダイニング
レンガＷ〞
まずは
スパークリングで乾杯
（荒澤さん）はい どうぞ
（吉田）オオッ…
これは… じゃ “チンチン”で
（荒澤さん）はい どうぞどうぞ
チンチンで　チンチン！
（室谷）チンチン
は～いはいはい チンチンで
ああ どうもどうも…
ちょっと おジャマします
（室谷）おジャマしま～す
（ﾅﾚｰﾀｰ）
酒場では 地元常連客に挨拶
これが吉田類の乾杯だ
おいしいですね
ハァ～ッ…
いいよね この爽やかな感じ
（荒澤さん）
これ 余市(よいち)産の白ツブなんですけど
白ワインで蒸しまして
クルクルッとやって食べてみて…
（吉田）
コリコリが残ってて…
これをスカッとした…
…スパークリングで流し込む
最高じゃないですかね？
（ﾅﾚｰﾀｰ）おつまみは
１皿200円からという―
うれしい価格のイタリアン
店主がイタリアで
食べ歩きをしたテイストを生かし
小樽の素材をミックス
深い味わいが ここにある
（室谷）
真っ黒い何か… 何でしょう？
（荒澤さん）これはですね
赤井川(あかいがわ)産の にんにくなんですけど
炊飯ジャー… 要は
保温だけの中に入れとくんです
20日間
（室谷）えっ？
そうすると
こういう状態になるんです
（吉田）あっ これ カラカラです
（室谷）でも
中は ちょっと柔らかいのかな？
ちょっと 食べるの 勇気が要ります
（吉田）あっ…
いや これ甘いじゃないですか
（荒澤さん）甘いです
ピスタチオのような香りがする
（吉田）うん！
いや こういう…
いや これは初めてですね 僕
（荒澤さん）ああ そうですか
（ナレーター）赤井川の
生産者が作る黒にんにく
炊飯ジャーで20日間
じっくり熟成させて
うまみを
引き出した ひと品
（吉田）
いかにも もう 通な感じですよね
イタリアに
行けば行くほどですね
あの… こういう感じが
好きなりまして
…で
こういうスタイルに
向こうのほうに見えるの あれ
ちょっとカウンター違いますよね？
（笑い声）
（室谷）手ぇ振ってくださってます
こんばんは
そちら 何なんですか？
なんか カウンター
何の… 何屋さんなんですか？
（真田さん）一応 すし屋さんッス
（室谷）おすし屋さん！
（ﾅﾚｰﾀｰ）イタリアンの屋台に
おすしカウンター？
小樽といえば
外せないキーワード
〝おすし〞
ウ～ン… 気になる！
（ナレーター）
〝人良し 味良し
酔いの良し〞
日本全国を巡る酒場詩人の吉田類
港町 小樽めぐり
レンガ横丁のイタリアンで
意外な物を発見！
（室谷）こんばんは
そちら 何なんですか？
なんか カウンター
何の… 何屋さんなんですか？
一応 すし屋さんッス
（室谷）おすし屋さん！
（ﾅﾚｰﾀｰ）なんと イタリアンバーの
カウンターの先には―
おすし屋さんが！
（吉田）
こっちでも食べられるんだ？
そうですね
経営は全然 別なんですけど
取ってもいいですか？
（荒澤さん）どうぞどうぞ 是非
何か おすしを！
（真田さん）おすし はい
えっと ６貫のでいいですか？
（吉田）６貫で
（真田さん）分かりました
なんとなく 僕の第六感で…
（笑い声）
（男性たち）“第六感で”
出ましたよ
オヤジギャグが出ましたよ
（ﾅﾚｰﾀｰ）
類さん 早くもエンジン全開！
本場職人が
握る立ち食いずし
すし屋 〝高大(こうだい)〞
握っている間に
類さん 白ワインを追加です
いや でも
こんなに楽しいお店があるとはね
僕は びっくりしましたね
（室谷）
ほかのお客さまと距離が近くてね
（荒澤さん）そうですね
だんだん こう 交じってくんですね
（笑い声）
（話し声）
（室谷）あっ！ 類さん おすしが…
（真田さん）おすし
（吉田）すごいですね これは
（室谷）
小樽といえば おすしですもんね
ちょっと 私 勢いに乗って
白ワインいただこうかしら
白ワイン はいよ！ 白ください
（荒澤さん）はいよ！
（吉田）フフッ…
この取り合わせが面白いよね これ
（笑い声）
（ﾅﾚｰﾀｰ）思わず 白ワインを
追加したくなるような おすし
小樽近海で
取れた魚を中心に
おいしい握りが並ぶ
これで ６貫１０００円
（室谷）
私 じゃ イクラをいただこうかな
ウン… ウ～ン！
プチプチッと おいしい！
類さん 私 お酒とワイン
一緒にいただくって初めてです
いやいや… あの…
“おすしとワイン”でしょう
ああっ… ハハッ…
私 今何て言いました？
（吉田）お酒とワイン
（室谷）失礼しました
酔っ払ってきましたよ
（笑い声）
楽しくなっちゃって フフッ…
（吉田）もう このノリだと…
もう ひけないよね
（真田さん）ひけないッスか？
もう 次 ちょっと
追加オーダーしていいですか？
はい
（拍手）
（真田さん）ありがとうございます
また 何だろう？ この拍手
（笑い声）
（女性）類さ～ん！
（男性）類さ～ん！
ちょ… ちょっとだけ あっちで
乾杯しに行きましょう
（室谷）そうですね
（吉田）あっ こっちは…
こっちは また違った雰囲気で
（真田さん）いらっしゃいませ！
（吉田）いいですね
乾杯！
ああ どうもどうも…
すばらしいよね
なに飲んでらっしゃるんですか？
（男性）芋ロック ハハハッ…
（真田さん）芋ロック 出た！
（室谷）芋ロック いいですね
大丈夫です まだ６杯目なんで
（真田さん）“まだ” ハハハッ…
（吉田）いい雰囲気ですね
（室谷）ねっ？ 楽しい
（荒澤さん）
これ… だけどね 毎晩やってると
もう やめれないですよ
あの… 楽しくて
（室谷）大将！
大将のオススメ どうなりました？
もう出来上がりました
（室谷）ありがとうございます
いやいや
待ってくださいよ ちょっと
網走(あばしり)産の釣りきんき
それと
網走の生のニシン
それと ヤリイカ
アートやね これは
（真田さん）アート？ アハハッ！
美しい！
（真田さん）言いますね
（ﾅﾚｰﾀｰ）正に おすしのアート！
大将オススメの旬の３貫握り
見事な出来栄えです
もうね これに関しては…
コメントなしで
ＯＫでしょう？ これで
（室谷）網走のニシン
ウ～ン… おいしい！
大将 おいひい！
（真田さん）“おいひい”
（室谷）めったらだ！
（吉田）
め… “めったらだ”で―
これ“めったにない
おいしさだよ”というね
これ 青森弁なんですよ
（室谷）すごい脂乗ってて
おいしいですね
これは あの… 小樽のね…
（荒澤さん）ヤリイカ
（吉田）うん
これも めったらだ
（室谷）めったらだ～！
（ﾅﾚｰﾀｰ）シメは 小樽のヤリイカ
自然の甘みが広がる日本海の味
ここで 酒場詩人 類さんに対抗し
室谷香菜子が突然 一句を披露
（客たち）ウ～ン…
いや これはね
なかなか耳障りがいい
（吉田）あの…
小樽飴をね 食べに行ったんです
（室谷）そうなんですよ
（吉田）屋台があるんですよね
（荒澤さん）朝 雨
降ってましたしね それに かけて…
（室谷）そうなんですよ！
（吉田）あっ よく分かりましたね
“飴”と“雨”をかけた…
分かってらっしゃる！
愛してるよ
（笑い声）
こま… 困ったもんだね これ
（室谷）楽しくなって…
（ﾅﾚｰﾀｰ）提灯(ちょうちん)が ともるころ
小樽の町は 笑い声に染まります
（客たち）乾杯！
（ﾅﾚｰﾀｰ）続いては
小樽っ子が集う洋風居酒屋
見たこともないスケールの
ベーコンに 室谷香菜子がほえる！
めってから
たんげめや これ
これね
今 訳しますけど…
（吉田）いや
さっきの立ち飲み 面白かったね
面白かったですね！
（吉田）ていうか―
ああいうのは もう
全国に広めたい感じがしますが
まだまだ時間 早いし
（室谷）はい
こちら！
（吉田）ここも また…
ここも 見てください
外観が変わってますよね すごく
“ぽんかす”なんですね？
（室谷）“ぽんかす”じゃないです
“すかんぽ”ですね
（吉田）あっ “すかんぽ”
逆ですね
（吉田）あっ そうですか
（ナレーター）
〝楽笑(らくしょう)酒場 すかんぽ〞
小樽っ子が集う
洋風居酒屋
（吉田）ちょっと
横 おジャマしていいですか
（男性）どうぞ
（吉田）すいません
（室谷）おジャマします
（田山さん）３度つぎってのも…
（吉田）えっ？ これ
３度つぎっての これ どういう…
（室谷）３度つぎ？
（田山さん）ちょっと
お時間いただくんですけど
（室谷）どのぐらいですか？
（田山さん）
５分ぐらい かかっちゃうんで…
（ﾅﾚｰﾀｰ）
完成まで５分かかる３度つぎビール
酒場通の類さんも初耳メニュー
一体 どういう物なのか？
今ちょっと こう グッと引いてから
放置したんですけど…
あれが
まず１度つぎということですか？
そうです １回目の…
（ﾅﾚｰﾀｰ）まずは１度つぎ
まだ 時間がかかりそうなので
類さんたち ほかのビールを頼み
ここでも やはり…
（吉田）よろしいですか？
すいません どうもどうも
（客たち）乾杯！
（吉田）どうも
（室谷）今ちょうど２回目ですね
時間かかるんだ…
（吉田）いや これ 多分ね
あしたまで かかっちゃう…
（笑い声）
（ﾅﾚｰﾀｰ）５分ですよ ５分
（吉田）ベーコンのステーキとか
ありますね
（田山さん）赤井川村って
いうとこで 黒豚を使って…
熟成のベーコンなんですけれども…
その前に
僕 お手洗い行ってきていい？
ハハッ… お手洗いですか？
どうぞどうぞ…
ちょっと まだ できてないと
思いますんでね
我慢は 体によくないですからね
どうぞどうぞ…
３度つぎ まだですか？
（田山さん）できちゃった
（室谷）あっ できました？
あら そうですか！
じゃ まだ できてないって
いうことに していただいてね
いや そういうわけに
いかないドリンクなんです
（室谷）類さん お手洗いに
行っちゃった　どうしよう…
これ！ こちらが
そのウワサの３度つぎビール
飲んじゃおっかな 先に
ごめんなさい 類さん
うん！
ああ！ 違いますね
（田山さん）はい
あの… まろやかな…
（田山さん）はい そうですね
スッと口の中に入ってくる
泡が おいしい！
類さん ちょっと！ まだかな？
（笑い声）
泡なくなってきちゃって…
（ナレーター）
１度つぎ… ２度つぎ…
３度つぎ
時間をかけて
仕上げるビールは―
炭酸が適度に抜けて
より ビールの味を
引き立てる
じっくり じっくり
待ってでも飲みたい珠玉の１杯
あっ 類さん
先に飲んじゃって ごめんなさいね
これが３度つぎ
（室谷）これが３度つぎ
ちょっと 改めて
（吉田）じゃ どうもどうも
（吉田･室谷）乾杯！
うわぁ めっちゃクリーミー！
この泡を飲むためにあるような
ビールじゃないですか？ これ
（室谷）あっ… わあ！
（吉田）オッ…
ああ やっぱり…
ねっ？ 美しいですね
（田山さん）
ありがとうございます
まあ ベーコンエッグ
なんですけども
卵も 余市町の
自然卵を使ってるんで
（室谷）ちょっと この黄身！
黄身の色が なんか すごく…
（吉田）太陽が いっぱい
太陽が いっぱい…
名付けて“太陽が いっぱい”
（室谷）
こんなに肉厚なベーコン 初めて！
これね
今 訳しますけど…
あの… 〝これ めったに
食べられないよ〞
〝こんな
おいしい味〞という…
グーッ！
（田山さん）ありがとうございます
（吉田）今の訳さんでいいか？
今 標準… 今の標準語でした
（ﾅﾚｰﾀｰ）
牧場で 丹念に作られた手作りの味
黒豚の熟成ベーコンステーキ
（田山さん）卵の黄身の色は
季節によって変わるんです
鶏たちが食べる餌が変わるので
（吉田･室谷）へえ…
（田山さん）今は 特にカボチャを
よく食べるんで 余計…
（吉田）それで こんな黄色が…
なんか こうなると―
どんどん ほかのメニュー
お願いしたくなりますね
ありがとうございます
（室谷）
なに召し上がってるんですか？
（男性）これ 角煮です
（室谷）わあ おいしそう！
（男性）田中(たなか)カクニ…
（笑い声）
（室谷）何ですって？
（男性）ハハッ… ごめん
（吉田）それじゃ もういっぺん
カクニンさせてもらいます
（男性）ああ…
（笑い声）
困ったね
（室谷）もう 酔っ払いばっかりだ
（ﾅﾚｰﾀｰ）
和の定番 豚の角煮をカクニン！
そして “すかんぽ”の
名物といえば こちら！
ソースたっぷりの
そばめし
そのお味は？
（吉田）このそばめし…
（田山さん）もともとは
神戸(こうべ)のほうの食べ物なんですけど
僕が ちょっと しばらく
向こうに いたことがあって
そのときに おいしかったので
是非 自分の店で
採用したいと思ったんですけど
焼きそばと ご飯と…
（吉田）うん！
ウ～ン！
（室谷）ウ～ン！
これ みやびに仕上がってますね
（田山さん）ハハハハッ…
これ めっちゃ上品じゃないですか
（室谷）上品！
（客たち）乾杯！
（室谷）じゃ
小樽のご出身ではないんですか？
（田山さん）はい
（室谷）また どうして小樽に？
旅の途中で
（室谷）旅の途中？
ええ ちょっと
寄ったもんですから
…で すごく気に入りまして
小樽に住むために
お店を開いたっていう…
同じやと思います
あの…
仲間に入れてくださいね フフッ…
マスターも類さんも 北海道にね…
大好きになって
そうです そうです…
そう思いますよ
いや マスター
あっ どうも
今日は ありがとうございます
いやいや ありがとうございます
このあと 小樽の夜に
吉田類が一句
（吉田）でも こういう…
（拍手と歓声）
この泡…
この泡が… この泡のために…
このお酒の向こうに
友がいるというね…
（室谷）ああ…
これがね うれしいじゃ
ありませんか
深いですねえ！
私 何にも考えないで
お酒
飲んでましたけれども
いや これからはね
感じてください
考えなくて
いいですから
感じるんですね
（吉田）感じるんです
（ナレーター）
おいしい酒に
おいしい料理
港町 小樽を
堪能しました